Partial Guide to the Memorial Library of Music Collection
Department of Special Collections
- Sylvia ou La nymphe de Diana. / DELIBES, CLEMENT PHILIBERT LEO (1836-1891), MLM 257
  Ballet en trois actes et cinq tableaux de MM. Jules Barbier & Mérante. Représenté pour la première fois à Paris sur la scene de l'Opéra, le mercredi 14 juin 1876. Musique de Léo Delibes. Partition piano... Paris, Henri Heugel, 1876. P1. no. H. 6041. First edition. Inscribed to Mlle. Jeanne Gounod by the composer. The inscription includes four bars of music from the score. This is not the first issue. It has the number 28184-4 at the bottom of the ""Personnages"" leaf (cf. entry for first edition, first issue).
- Sylvia. Valse lente. / DELIBES, CLEMENT PHILIBERT LEO (1836-1891), MLM 258
  Manuscript fragment signed. 1886. 1 leaf (1 page) 18 x 111/2 cm. Inserted in the first edition, first issue, of the piano and vocal score. [See item no. 256].
- 2 Stücke für kleines Orchester. / DELIUS, FREDERICK (1862-1934), MLM 259
  I. On hearing the first cuckoo in spring. Beim ersten Kuckucksruf im Frühling. II. Summer night on the river. Sommer-nacht am Flusse. Partitur... Tischner & Jagenberg, c1913. P1. no. 248. At head of title: Frederick Delius. First edition.
- Over the hills and far away. Fantasia. / DELIUS, FREDERICK (1862-1934), MLM 260
  Original manuscript signed. 1897. 21 leaves (38 pages) 27 x 36 cm.
- Cyrca. Action chorégraphique et symphonique en un act de Albert Boucheron et Paul de Choudens. Musique de Marc Delmas. Partition piano et chant. Paris, Choudens [c1928] Pl. no. A. C. 15,078. First edition. Inscribed to Mlle. de Craponne by the composer. Mlle de Craponne danced the title role in the ballet." / DELMAS, MARC (MARIE JEAN BAPTISTE) (1885-1931), MLM 261
- Autographed Letter to Mrs. Kingston / Deriza, L.1881 Dec. 16, MLM 261A
- Issé: Pastorale heroique. / Destouches, André, MLM 261B
  First complete edition.
- The padlock. / DIBDIN, CHARLES (1745-1814), MLM 262
  A comic opera as it is performed at the Theatre-Royal in Drury Lane. The words by the author of the Maid of the mill; &c. &c. The music by Mr. Dibdin. London, Printed for the author & sold by J. Johnston [1768] The text is by Isaac Bickerstaffe. First edition. Presented for the first time at London, 1768. Wotquenne, 3596.
- Poor Tom, or The sailor's epitaph." / DIBDIN, CHARLES (1745-1814), MLM 263
  Written and composed by Mr. Dibdin for his entertainment called the Oddities. London, The author [ca. 1790] First edition. Signed by the composer. Vocal score with score for ""Flute or guittar"" and ""Guittar in F"" at the end.
- [Betly ossia La capanna svizzera] ""Duetto aggiunto del Maestro Donizetti pella Betly in due atti per soprano e basso.""" / DONIZETTI, GAETANO (1797-1848), MLM 264
  Original manuscript. 1836. 15 leaves (29 pages) 391/2 x 28 cm. The one-act opera Betly ossia La capanna svizzera was first performed at the Teatro Nuovo in Naples, July 24, 1836. Its libretto used Scribe's Châlet on which Adolphe Adam's most successful one-act opera Le châlet was based. Donizetti enlarged the opera to two acts and this duet was written for the enlarged version. Numerous corrections indicate Donizetti's haste to complete the score for the fall season in Palermo in 1836.
- Don Pasquale. / DONIZETTI, GAETANO (1797-1848), MLM 265
  Opéra bouffe en 3 actes. Musique de G. Donizetti avec accompagt. de piano par Th. Labarre. Représenté pour la ler fois, sur la Scène Italienne de Paris le 3 janvier, 1843... Paris, La France Musicale [1843] Pl. no F.M. 260. First edition.
- Autograph letter signed. / DONIZETTI, GAETANO (1797-1848), MLM 265A
  This was written to Tomaso Persico, his financial adviser, from Vienna February 21, 1843. It refers inter alia to Don Pasquale.
- Don Sebastian. Finale, act 4." / DONIZETTI, GAETANO (1797-1848), MLM 266
  Autograph manuscript. Ca. 1843. 1 leaf (2 pages) 35 x 271/2 cm.
- La fille du régiment. / DONIZETTI, GAETANO (1797-1848), MLM 267
  Opéra comique en 2 actes. Paroles de Mr. Bayard et St. Georges. Musique de G. Donizetti... Paris, Schonenberger [ca. 1840] P1. no. S. 653. First edition. Orchestral score. Presented for the first time at Paris, February 11, 1840.
- [La fille du régiment] Madlle. / DONIZETTI, GAETANO (1797-1848), MLM 268
  Jenny Lind's songs in La figlia del reggimento [by Gaetano Donizetti] ... No. 4. The home of the brave. London, Duff & Hodgson [1847] P1. no. 1227. Jenny Lind's copy.
- La fille du regiment. / DONIZETTI, GAETANO (1797-1848), MLM 269
  .. Polka on airs from La fille du régiment [by] Donizetti. London [1847] P1. no. 147. Jenny Lind's copy.
- [La fille du régiment] The rataplan. / DONIZETTI, GAETANO (1797-1848), MLM 270
  Sung by Jenny Lind in Donizetti's opera, La fille du régiment. London [1847] P1. no. 197. Jenny Lind's copy. Text in French and English.
- [Invito alla danza] / DONIZETTI, GAETANO (1797-1848), MLM 271
  Piano and vocal score. ca. 1844. Original manuscript signed. sketch for a song. 1 leaf (1 page) 34 x 26 cm.
- L'Elisir d'amore. / DONIZETTI, GAETANO (1797-1848), MLM 272
  Opera in due atti del maestro Donizetti... Paris, Bernard Latte [1839] P1. no. B. L. 1861. First French edition. Piano and vocal score. Presented for the first time at Milan, March 12, 1832. Text in Italian.
- Lucia di Lammermoor. / DONIZETTI, GAETANO (1797-1848), MLM 273
  Dramma tragico di Salvadore Cammarano. Musica del... G. Donizetti. Per canto con accomp. di piano forte... Chiasso, Stamperia di musica l'Euterpe ticinese [ca. 1835] P1. nos. 286-292, 299, 293-296. Presented for the first time at Naples, June 7, 1836.
- Lucrezia Borgia. / DONIZETTI, GAETANO (1797-1848), MLM 274
  Melodramma posto in musica dal Maestro Gaetano Donizetti... Milano, Gio. Ricordi [1833] P1. nos. 7400-7407, 7410-7413, 7408-7409, 7417-7420, 7414-7416. First edition. Piano and vocal score. Presented for the first time at Milan, December 26, 1833.
- Autograph letter signed. / DONIZETTI, GAETANO (1797-1848), MLM 274A
  This was written to ""Teodoro"" from Vienna [ca. 1844] The composer mentions the Naples performance of some of his operas including Catarina Cornaro and of intrigues against him there.
- Le frère Philippe. / DOURLEN, VICTOR CHARLES PAUL (1780-1864), MLM 275
  Opéra comique en un acte en prose. Paroles de M. Auguste Duport. Musique de Mr. Dourlen... Paris, Ph. Petit [1818] P1. no. 8.P. First edition. Orchestral score. Presented for the first time at Paris, January 20, 1818. Wolffheim, II, 1387; Wotquenne, 1534.
- A collection of canzonetts in the handwriting of Dragonetti. / DRAGONETTI, DOMENICO(1763-1846), MLM 276
  Original manuscript signed. 10 leaves (17 pages) 33 x 23cm.
- Des Evangelischen Zions musicalische Harmonie. / DRETZEL, CORNELIUS HEINRICH, MLM 277
  Oder: Evangelisches Choral-Buch, worinnen die wahre Melodien/ derer so wohl in denen beeden Marggrafthümern Bayreuth und Onoltzbach/ als auch in der Stadt Nürnberg, deren Gebiete und andern Evangelischen Gemeinen üblichen Kirchen-Lieder, mit aufmerksamste
- Après la moisson. / DUBOIS, FRANCOIS CLEMENT THEODORE (1837-1924), MLM 278
  Scène chorale pour voix d'hommes. Paroles de Pierre Barbier. Musique de Théodore Dubois. Paris, Heugel [ca. 1893] P1. no. H. et Cie. 7508. Caption title. First edition. Inscribed to [Charles] Warot by the composer.
- Messe solennelle. / DUBOIS, FRANCOIS CLEMENT THEODORE (1837-1924), MLM 279
  Choeurs, soli et grand orchestre, par Th. Dubois. Original manuscript signed. Roma, 1863. 75 leaves (150 pages consisting of 2 title-pages, 145 music, and 3 blank. A leaf with two pages of music in pencil attached to p. 98 has not been counted in the collation) 37 x 28 cm. Two title-pages in the composer's handwriting, the second as above. The first reads: ""Messe pontificale, Ière version, Inédite dans cette forme"" and inscribed: ""Souvenir affectueux à mon éditeur et ami Mr. Ad. Pérégally. Paris, 16 avril 1894. Th. Dubois.""
- Poème de mai. / DUBOIS, FRANCOIS CLEMENT THEODORE (1837-1924), MLM 280
  Poésie de Armand Silvestre. Musique de Théodore Dubois... pour tenor ou soprano. Paris, Alphonse Leduc. Pl. no. A. L. 6848. First edition. Inscribed to Mme. Enoch by the composer.
- Les sept paroles du Christ. / DUBOIS, FRANCOIS CLEMENT THEODORE (1837-1924), MLM 281
  Pour soil, choeurs et orchestre par Th Dubois. Réduction de piano par l'auteur... Paris, Heugel [ca. 1867] P1. no. G.H. 434 (H. et Cie. 7078 on p. [I]) Inscribed to Mlle. Henri Donon-Maigrot by the composer.
- Traité de contrepoint et de fugue / DUBOIS, FRANCOIS CLEMENT THEODORE (1837-1924), MLM 282
  par Théodore Dubois... Paris, Heugel [c1901] P1. no. H. & Cie. 20404. First edition. Inscribed by the composer.
- L'apprenti-sorcier. / DUKAS, PAUL (1865-1935), MLM 283
  Scherzo d'après une ballade de Goethe, par Paul Dukas. Partition d'orchestre... Paris, A. Durand & Fils [ca. 1897] Pl no. D. & F. 5302. First edition. Inscribed to Mr. L. A. Bourgault-Ducoudray by the composer.
- Ariane et Barbe-Bleue. / DUKAS, PAUL (1865-1935), MLM 284
  Conte en trois actes. Poème de Maurice Maeterlinck. Musique de Paul Dukas. Partition pour chant et piano réduite par l'auteur. Paris. A. Durand & Fils, c1906. P1. no. D. & F. 6572. First edition.
- La péri. / DUKAS, PAUL (1865-1935), MLM 285
  Poème dansé [de] Paul Dukas. Partition d'orchestre. Paris, A. Durand & Fils [c1911] P1. no. D. & F. 8201. First edition.
- Variations, interlude et finale pour piano sur un thème de J. Ph. Rameau, par Paul Dukas / DUKAS, PAUL (1865-1935), MLM 286
  Paris, A. Durand & Fils [1902] P1. no. D. & F. 6087. First edition. Inscribed to Paul Poujaud by the composer.
- Stabat Mater a tre voci con ripieni di Francesco Durante. / DURANTE, FRANCESCO (1684-1755), MLM 287
  Original manuscript. 31 leaves (title-page, 60 pages) The first eight pages are not in Durante's hand. The manuscript lacks eight pages. Works by Durante were not published, according to Riemann, during the composer's life and the existence of a Stabat Mater remained unknown. It calls for three solo voices (two sopranos and alto) and a two-voice chorus (soprano and alto). The great importance of the manuscript is evident.
- Dussek, Jan Ladislav" / DURANTE, FRANCESCO (1684-1755), MLM 287A
  [Songs]
- Rusalka (The water witch) / DVORAK, ANTONIN (1841-1904), MLM 288
  Manuscript fragment signed. 111/2 x 81/2 cm. Four bars from the score.
- [Seven gypsy songs] Opus 55, no.4." / DVORAK, ANTONIN (1841-1904), MLM 289
  Manuscript signed. 1900. 1 leaf (1 page) 24 x 331/2 cm. The manuscript of the first stanza of ""Songs my mother taught me"" for piano and voice with the Czech text. Inscribed to Blanche Marchesi, the famous singer. This is probably the most popular song composed by Dvorák.
- Sonatine für Violine und Pianoforte von Ant. Dvorák. Op. 100. / DVORAK, ANTONIN (1841-1904), MLM 290
  Berlin, N. Simrock, 1894. P1. no. 10238. First edition. Inscribed by the composer.
- The Spectre's Bride / DVORAK, ANTONIN (1841-1904), MLM 290A
- Autograph letter signed. / DVORAK, ANTONIN (1841-1904), MLM 290B
  To [Francesco] Berger of the Philharmonic Society, London, February 18, 1896. Refers to his forthcoming visit to London.
- Stabat Mater for soli, chorus and orchestra, composed by Anton Dvorák. / DVORAK, ANTONIN (1841-1904), MLM 291
  Op. 58...London, Novello [1884] At head of title: Novello's original octavo edition. Signed by Emma Albani, Janet Patey, Edward Lloyd, Charles Santley, J. T. Carrodus, and the composer. Vocal score with Latin text.
- The apostles (Parts I and II) An oratorio by Edward Elgar. / ELGAR, SIR EDWARD (1857-1934), MLM 292
  (Op. 49)...London, Novello, c1903. Pl. no. 11645. At head of title: Novello's original octavo edition. First produced at the Birmingham Musical Festival, October, 1903. Inscribed by the composer.
- La Capricieuse. / ELGAR, SIR EDWARD (1857-1934), MLM 292A
  Op. 17, 1893.
- Cockaigne (In London town) Concert overture for full orchestra, composed by Edward Elgar. / ELGAR, SIR EDWARD (1857-1934), MLM 293
  (Op. 40) Full orchestral score... London, c1901. Pl. no. H 3239. First edition. Inscribed to Sir August Manns by the composer.
- Concerto. / ELGAR, SIR EDWARD (1857-1934), MLM 294
  Edward Elgar. Op. 61. [London] Novello, c1910. P1. no. 13292. Caption title. Inscribed to Eugene Ysaÿe by the composer. Piano and violin score. Stamped ""Proof copy-private.""
- Liebesgrüss für Violine mit Begleitung Pianoforte. / ELGAR, SIR EDWARD (1857-1934), MLM 295
  Edward Elgar. Op. 6. July 1888. Original manuscript. 3 leaves (6pages) 261/2 x 35 cm.
- Salut d'amour for solo piano. / ELGAR, SIR EDWARD (1857-1934), MLM 295A
  Urtext edition by Donald Burrows.
- Salut d'amour for violin and piano. / ELGAR, SIR EDWARD (1857-1934), MLM 295B
- Symphony no. 2 (in E-flat) for full orchestra, composed by Edward Elgar. (Op. 63)" / ELGAR, SIR EDWARD (1857-1934), MLM 296
  ... London, Novello, c1911. First edition. Inscribed by the composer.
- Te Deum and Benedictus. / ELGAR, SIR EDWARD (1857-1934), MLM 296A
  In F, Op. 34. Composed for the Hereford Music Festival. 1897. London, New York. Inscribed by the Composer. (Edward Elgar)
- Variations on an original theme for orchestra composed by Edward Elgar. (Op. 36). / ELGAR, SIR EDWARD (1857-1934), MLM 297
  Arranged for pianoforte by the composer.. London, Novello (c1899) Pl. no. 10815. First edition. Bound with this is the original manuscript signed (cf. separate entry).Elgar was not generally appraised at his true worth until the performance of the ""Enigma"" Variations under Richter in 1899. The nobility of this music is a measure of the composer's appreciation of his great friend and adviser, A. J. Jaeger of the Novello publishing house-the ""Nimrod"" of the composition.
- Variations for orchestra composed by Edward Elgar. Op. 36 / ELGAR, SIR EDWARD (1857-1934), MLM 298
  (Arrangement for pianoforte solo). Original manuscript signed. 1899. 34 leaves (47 pages). Bound with the first edition of the score.
- Octuor (ut majeur) pour 4 violons, 2 altos et 2 violoncellos." / ENESCO, GEORGES (1881-), MLM 299
  Original manuscript signed. 2 leaves (4pages) 27 x 351/2 cm. Inscribed to Mme. Blanche Marchesi, June 24, 1904.
- Silence! / ENESCO, GEORGES (1881-), MLM 300
  Original manuscript signed. April 23, 1905. 3 leaves (title-page, 4 pages) 261/2 x 351/2 cm. Inscribed to Mlle. Victoire Péridé. The text is from Albert Samain's Jardin de l'Infante.
- Trois rhapsodies roumaines. Op. 11. / ENESCO, GEORGES (1881-), MLM 301
  Paris, Enoch [ca. 1914] P1. no. 6060. At head of title: Georges Enesco. First edition. Contents: 2e Rhapsodie roumaine. Orchestral score.
- Le bon gîte. / ERLANGER, CAMILLE (1863-1919), MLM 302
  Original manuscript. 4 leaves (4 pages). Piano and vocal score. The song is by Paul Déroulide.
- 1896-1903. Le fils de l'étoile. / ERLANGER, CAMILLE (1863-1919), MLM 303
  Poème de Catulle Mendès. Musique de Camille Erlanger. Paris, Société Nouvelle d'Editions Musicales, 1903. P1. no. P. D. 3280. Caption-title. First edition. Inscribed to Mme. Armand Rohrbach by the Library composer. This copy is stamped ""Epreuve.""
- Poëmes russes. / ERLANGER, CAMILLE (1863-1919), MLM 304
  Mis en vers par Catulle Mendès. Musique de Camille Erlanger. Illustrations de Pal... Paris, Paul Dupont [ca. 1915] First edition. Inscribed to Mme. Chéreau by the composer. Contents: I. ""Aubade"" (Fête), 2. ""Les larmes humaine"" (Tioutchev), 3. ""Printemps"" (Tioutchev), 4. ""Les seuls pleurs"" (Nékrassov), 5. ""L'ange et l'âme"" (Lermontov), 6. ""Fédia"" (Tourguénev). Inserted is a leaf (1 page) with the text of ""Les larmes humaine"" in Erlanger's handwriting.
- La sorcière. / ERLANGER, CAMILLE (1863-1919), MLM 305
  Drame musical en 4 actes et 5 tableaux d'après Victorien Sardou par André Sardou. Musique de Camille Erlanger... Paris, Office Musical, c1912. Pl. no. O. 280 M. First edition. Inscribed to Arthur Bernède by the composer. Piano and vocal score.
- El amor brujo. / FALLA Y MATHEU, MANUEL MARIA DE (1876-1946), MLM 306
  Manuscript fragment signed. 1 leaf (1 page) 24 x 181/2 cm. Four bars from the movement ""Tranquillo e misterioso"" for piano and strings.
- El retablo de maese Pedro. / FALLA Y MATHEU, MANUEL MARIA DE (1876-1946), MLM 306A
  1823
- Trois mélodies (Théophile Gautier) Les colombes, Chinoiserie, Séguedille / FALLA Y MATHEU, MANUEL MARIA DE (1876-1946), MLM 307
  .. Paris, Rouart, Lerolle, c1910. P1. nos. R. L. & Cie. 9635-9637. At head of title: Manuel de Falla. First edition. Inscribed by the composer. Piano and vocal score.
- La vie brève (La vida breve) / FALLA Y MATHEU, MANUEL MARIA DE (1876-1946), MLM 308
  Drame lyrique en 2 actes et 4 tableaux de Carlos Fernandez-Shaw. Adaptation française de Paul Milliet. Musique de Manuel de Falla. Partition complète pour chant et piano (avec paroles françaises et le texte original espagnol) ... Paris, Max Eschig, c1913. P1. no. M. E. 400. First edition.
- Barcarolle pour piano par Gabriel Fauré. Op. 26 / FAURE, GABRIEL URBAIN (1845-1924), MLM 309
  ... Paris, J. Maho [1883] P1. no. J. 1897 H. First edition. Inscribed by the composer.
- 2me. Impromptu (en fa mineur) pour piano par Gabriel Fauré. Op. 31. / FAURE, GABRIEL URBAIN (1845-1924), MLM 310
  Paris, J. Hamelle [ca. 1913] Pl. no. J. 2119 H. First edition. Inscribed by the composer.
- Mazurka (si b majeur) pour piano par Gabriel Fauré. Op. 32 / FAURE, GABRIEL URBAIN (1845-1924), MLM 311
  ... Paris, J. Hamelle [ca. 1883] P1. no. J. 2120 H. First edition. Inscribed to Emmanuel Chabrier by the composer.
- Manuscript. / FAURE, GABRIEL URBAIN (1845-1924), MLM 311A
- Pénélope. / FAURE, GABRIEL URBAIN (1845-1924), MLM 312
  Poème lyrique en trois actes de René Fauchois. Musique de Gabriel Fauré. Partition chant et piano... Paris, Heugel [c1913] Pl. no. H. & Cie 24,214. First edition.
- An autograph letter signed. / FAURE, GABRIEL URBAIN (1845-1924), MLM 312A
  To Massenet, Bologna, October 27, 1878. Refers to Massenet's Le roi de Lahore.
- Requiem pour soli, choeurs & orchestre [Opus 48] / FAURE, GABRIEL URBAIN (1845-1924), MLM 313
  Partition chant & piano... [par Roger Ducasse] Paris, J. Hamelle [1900] P1. no. J. 4531 H. At head of title: Gabriel Fauré. First edition. Inscribed to M. Brancour by the composer.
- Songs / FAURE, GABRIEL URBAIN (1845-1924), MLM 313A [Bound with item no. 313B]
- Songs / FAURE, GABRIEL URBAIN (1845-1924), MLM 313B [Bound with item no. 313A]
- Thème et variations pour piano par Gabriel Fauré. Op. 73 / FAURE, GABRIEL URBAIN (1845-1924), MLM 314
  ... Concours du Conservatoire de Paris (1910). Paris, J. Hamelle [1910] P1. no. J. 4071 H. First edition. Inscribed to René Brancour by the composer.
- [Qui tollis] / FENAROLI, FEDELE (1730-1818), MLM 315
  For soprano and orchestra. Original manuscript. 9 leaves (17 pages) 30 x 221/2 cm. Fenaroli, a pupil of Durante and subsequently teacher of Cimarosa and Zingarelli at the Conservatorio della Pietà in Naples, wrote chiefly ecclesiastical works. A learned musician and rigid teacher, he established an extraordinary reputation as a theorist and his text book on the art of accompaniment from a figured bass had to be reprinted often. The Qui tollis for soprano and orchestra, two oboes, clarinets, bassoons, horns, strings, and organ in E-flat remained unpublished. It shows, as a typical Neapolitan creation, the influence of the opera in design, character, and detail.
- La femme nue. / FEVRIER, HENRI (1875-), MLM 316
  Drame lyrique en quatre actes d'après Henry Bataille. Paroles de Louis Payen. Musique de Henry Février. La partition chant et piano. Paris, Heugel [1932] P1. no. 28649. First edition. Inscribed to M. Cancalon by the composer. Presented for the first time at Paris, April 25, 1932.
- Gismonda. / FEVRIER, HENRI (1875-), MLM 317
  Drame lyrique en quatre acres d'après Victorien Sardou. Poème de Henri Cain et Louis Payen. Musique de Henry Février. Partition chant et piano... Paris, Heugel [c1919] PL no. H. & Cie. 26,357. First edition. Inscribed to Marthe Chenal by the composer.
- Monna Vanna. / FEVRIER, HENRI (1875-), MLM 318
  Drame lyrique en quatre actes de Maurice Maeterlinck. Musique de Henry Février. Partition piano et chant. Paris, Heugel, C1908. P1. no. H. & Cie. 23494. Inscribed to Mlle. Suzanne Astruc by the composer.
- Le roi aveugle. / FEVRIER, HENRI (1875-), MLM 319
  Opéra en 2 acres de Hugues le Roux. Traduction allemande de M.-D. Calvocoressi... Paris, Enoch, c1906. P1. no. E. & c. 6013. At head of title: Henri Février. First edition. Inscribed by the composer. Piano and vocal score.
- Sonate pour piano et violon par Henry Février. / FEVRIER, HENRI (1875-), MLM 320
  Paris, A. Quinzard [ca. 1910] P1. no. A. Q. & Cie. 961. First edition. Inscribed by the composer.
- Introduction and rondo for the piano forte on Blewitt's celebrated cavatina ""Come again, come again.""" / FIELD, JOHN (1782-1837), MLM 321
  Composed by John Field. London, Collard & Collard [1834] P1. no. 3598. First edition. Inscribed to Emma Burbige by the composer.
- A new fantasia for the piano forte, composed & arranged from the subject of the popular melody of We met." / FIELD, JOHN (1782-1837), MLM 322
  Most humbly dedicated to His Imperial Majesty, the Emperor of Russia by John Field of Petersburgh... London, Published for the proprietor of the ""Songs of the boudoir"" by Betts [1835] First edition. Inscribed by the composer.
- Nocturne, no. 5 (L'incendie par l'orage)" / FIELD, JOHN (1782-1837), MLM 323
  Original manuscript. 2 leaves (3 pages) 281/2 x 21 cm. Field, an Irish pianist, was a pupil of Clementi. He spent most of his life in Russia, hence his nickname, ""Russian"" Field. His nocturnes, setting the form and style for these pieces, were the models Chopin used in developing his own popular works. This particular composition is the best known of all his nocturnes. Violinists particularly have made it their own. The manuscript came from the collection of Prince Dolgorouki and bears his stamp. It was given to him by Robert Müller, Naples, January 26, 1840, and is so inscribed at the end. Bound with this are a manuscript fragment written by Field, a photograph of his portrait by James Lonsdale, an autograph letter signed from W. H. Grattan Flood to Arthur Hill, November 7, 1925, referring to the portrait, and an autograph letter signed from Field to Fétis, February 8, 1832.
- Composition without title for piano. Fragment. / FIELD, JOHN (1782-1837), MLM 324
  Original manuscript. ca. 1794. 1 leaf (1 page) 28 x 141/2 cm. This was written for Mrs. Alpe of Hardingham Hall near Attleborough, Norfolk. A note signed by Mrs. Alpe written at the head of the score reads: ""Composed by John Field (aged 12 years) afterwards Pianiste to the Emperor of Russia and given to me by him, in the presence of Mr. Clementi, in the year 1795."" Bound with the original manuscript of Field's Nocturne. No. 5.
- Wiegenlied von Gotter. / FLIESS, BERNHARD VON (1768-1840), MLM 325
  Original manuscript signed. 1 leaf (1 page) 32 x 24 cm. The first version of this famous lullaby, probably the most popular one ever composed, was erroneously attributed to Mozart and included in Breitkopf & Härtel's edition of Mozart's complete works.
- Notte amica. / FLORIMO, FRANCESCO (1800-1888), MLM 326
  Piano and vocal score of a song without title beginning ""Notte amica."" Original manuscript. 2 leaves (4 pages) 28 x 39 cm. A very rare manuscript of the distinguished archivist, historian, chronicler of Naples' musical institutions, and most intimate friend of V. Bellini. The composition, being in the key b minor, contains 16 bars. The voice part covering the third stanza is written separately and breaks off in the eighth measure. Serious circumstances must have prevented Florimo from writing down the last lines and inserting the title and dedication. Nevertheless the composition as such is complete.
- Martha. / FLOTOW, FRIEDRICH, FREIHERR VON (1812-1883), MLM 327